这里肯定以前是一块大陆 现在变成了两个大陆块
Where there are now two land masses, there once was just one.
叶之书肯定就在这儿
The Book of Leaves has to be here.
不惜一切手段找到探子 行动要快
Take whatever steps are necessary to find our spy. Do it quickly.
摧毁洛伦佐和所有支持他的人 这是神的旨意
It is God's will to break Lorenzo and all who support him.
就达芬奇的部分 我可能有些异议
With the exception of Da Vinci, I agree with you.
他制造出的武器 反而可以为我们所用
Those weapons he makes, they could all be ours.
罗马人多势强 天时地利
Rome has more men, and the Lord, on its side.
我们有十架管风琴火炮
Well, we've got ten pipe organ muskets
一分钟可以连续发射33次
capable of firing 33 rounds a minute on ours.
十架火炮? 谢谢你告诉我
Ten guns? Good to know. Thank you for that.
盖有罗马密印的信
Papers with the papal seal.
以及藏匿的地点
A list of locations to hide them.
- 你在哪儿找到的?  - 在贝奇先生的住处
- Where did you find this?  - Signor Becchi's quarters.
原来叛徒是你
The traitor was you.
洛伦佐 这是场误会
Lorenzo, this is a mistake.
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hd.cnscg.com/ ==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调：影子
时间轴：暗之忆
翻译：SceneryJuly 竺
校对：竺 影子
达芬奇的恶魔 第一季 第4集
孩子
Boy.
芬奇镇 11年前
我的一个猎人想装饰这盾牌
One of my huntsmen wishes this decorated.
你很有天赋 画一下吧
You've a keen eye. Paint it.
莱昂纳多十四岁的时候
When Leonardo was 14 years old,
他的父亲皮耶罗发现他很有天分
his father, Piero, having found little use for the young man,
便给他一件工作
gave him a task.
第二天 莱昂捕捉了各种各样生物
Leo spent the next day collecting all manner of strange creatures.
他花了很长时间解剖它们
And so long did he labor dissecting them
虽然臭味令人难以忍受
that the stench was past bearing.
但莱昂纳多并不在意
But Leonardo didn't notice,
他对艺术是多么热爱啊
so great was his love for his art.
我完成了 父亲! 来看看吧
It's finished, Father! Come see.
做得不错
It will suffice.
瞒着那个猎人
Knowing that the hunting guide would be none the wiser,
皮耶罗还给他一块新盾牌
Piero presented him with a new shield,
把旧盾牌以一百达科特的价钱
while selling the original one to a vendor
卖给了小贩
for 100 ducats.
后来小贩又以三百达科特的价钱
And then the vendor resold it to the Duke of Milan himself
卖给了米兰公爵
for 300 ducats.
后来皮耶罗很不情愿地
Loath to pass up such a resource,
把他的儿子交给我指导
Piero arranged for his son to be brought under my tutelage.
我给了中间人五十达科特
I paid a finder's fee of 50 ducats.
在我看来非常划算
A bargain, in my estimation.
他父亲卖给你一个小混蛋
His father sold you a bastard son.
是啊 但你知道吗?
Yes. But you know what?
要是能再有一个他这样的人
I would trade 100 of you
我愿意拿一百个你们这样的人来换
to have another one like him on my doorstep.
我觉得你喝多了 老头
I think you're drunk, old man.
你是嫉妒吧 波提切利
And you're jealous, Botticelli.
明天... 我就能醒酒
Tomorrow... I'll be sober.
但你还是会嫉妒
But you'll still be jealous.
你今天心事重重的
You're preoccupied today.
作画...
Painting...
不只是用笔画画那样简单
is about... it's about more than just strokes.
还要讲究视角
There's perspective.
我是应该从下面的角度画你...
I mean, do I paint you from below...
还是应该...
or do I paint you...
从上面呢?
from above?
还要讲究象征
And then there's symbols.
我要不要画你抱着只狗呢?
Do I paint you with a dog in your arms?
狗是忠诚的象征
It's a symbol of loyalty.
还有颜色 用一点朱红色...
Color. How about the particular shade of vermillion...
画你脸颊的红润怎么样?
that I use for the blush of your cheeks?
还有裙子的褶皱
And the folds of your dress.
应该是...
Should they be...
雍容华贵的...
lush and sumptuous...
还是平整带角的?
or stiff and angular?
或许...
And perhaps...
完全不画礼服
no gown at all.
要是我守本分的话
If I was a dutiful servant,
我会考虑雇主的要求
I'd consider the needs of my patron.
但我不守本分 所以...
But I'm not, so that...
我才心事重重
That is what I struggle with.
你一直在看那个
You can't take your eyes off that.
它有什么好看的?
What's so beautiful about it?
它和你一样 都很神秘
It's the same thing I see in you. It's a mystery.
它是个迷
It's a puzzle,
我会不顾一切地解开它
and I will stop at nothing to figure it out.
弗朗西斯科
Francesco.
我马焦雷教堂的墙都快塌了
The walls of my Cappella Maggiore lean and crumble,
就像罗马城一样破败不堪
just as Rome itself is in disrepair.
我一定要在这建座雄伟的教堂
This place must become a grand palace of the Lord,
用大理石圣殿
celebrating his glory in marble
和世上最优秀的画作
and majestic brushstrokes
庆祝主的荣耀
from the most enlightened hands on earth.
我要建一座精美的教堂
I will build a gleaming chapel
在天顶画上基督和摩西的故事
with the stories of Christ and Moses frescoed on the ceiling.
作为礼物献给永恒仁慈的上帝
A tribute to the everlasting grace of God.
我保证 陛下
I can assure you, Your Holiness,
如果您能把您的存款从美第奇银行...
if you move your accounts from the Medici Bank...
转到我的银行里来 您就能获得充足的资金
to my own, you'll have all the funds you need.
这不只需要资金
This will require more than funds.
重生需要毁灭
Resurrection requires death.
现在
And in this case,
罗马的重生
the sacrifice for Rome's rebirth
需要牺牲佛罗伦萨
will be Florence.
可是 我们不知道能否击败美第奇家族
However, the Medici have certain capabilities we are unsure we can best.
我们已经尝试过一次正面进攻了
We've tried a frontal assault.
我们需要你进行一些
We may need you to develop
其它的... 暗中破坏
other... less direct contingencies.
美第奇家族
The Medicis are the reason
把佛罗伦萨变成了巫师和鸡奸者的避难所
Florence is a sanctuary for sorcerers and... sodomites.
他们在这城里亵渎上帝
They've turned my city away from the Lord.
神父 我们要一起挽救这座城
Together, Holy Father, we will turn it back.
召集你的部下 捷洛拉莫
Now gather your men, Girolamo.
你也有任务要做
You've a role to play in this as well.
他一生都和咱的家族在一起
He's been with our family his entire life.
是他教我们识的字母
He taught us our letters.
我不管他抱没抱过你尿尿
I don't care if he held your prick when you first took a piss.
贝奇无疑是间谍和叛徒
Becchi is a spy and a traitor.
他的姐夫欠了大笔债
His brother-in-law carries epic debts
只有我们查获的罗马银币才能偿还
which could only be met with the Roman scudos we found.
我们破解了他藏匿信件的密文
We broke the cipher in dozens of letters he hid.
发现一封比一封罪孽深重
Each one more incriminating than the last.
现在不是仁慈的时间
Now is not the time to show mercy.
所以我们把老朋友抓起来 和疯子达芬奇交朋友
So we're jailing old friends while making new friends with lunatics like Da Vinci.
我们祖父也和疯子交过朋友
Our grandfather made friends with lunatics.
布鲁内列斯基也是疯子 可他建造了欧洲最雄伟的教堂
Brunelleschi was one and he created the most majestic cathedral in Europe.
要是你相信贝奇会叛变
If you believe Becchi betrayed us,
那你才是疯了
it's you who's gone mad.
洛伦佐!
Lorenzo!
不要! 求求你!
No! No, please!
告诉我 你知道亚伯拉罕对所多玛和蛾摩拉城的祷告是什么吗?
Tell me, are you familiar with Abraham's prayer for Sodom and Gomorrah?
他一开始承诺能在两座罪恶之城里
How many righteous people did Abraham initially promise
找到多少正直的人?
he would find in those blighted cities?
二十个?
20?
很不幸
Unfortunate.
不! 求求你!
No! Please!
你说是多少?
And your answer?
不知道? 不知道?
No? No?
不知道吗?
No idea?
这破地方没有忠诚的人了吗
Are there no faithful in this forsaken place
还是所有人都被诅咒了?
or are you all damned?
你 站起来
You. Stand.
我们期望你知道答案
Let us pray you know the right reply.
多少?
What?
五十人! 先生
50! Signor.
答对了
You are correct.
你把这封信带给美第奇家族
You will deliver this message to the Medicis.
里面详细描述了
It contains, in exacting detail,
今天这里发生的事情
the horrors witnessed here today.
瑞阿里奥 我们到底来这干嘛?
Why in God's name are we here, Riario?
告诉我 队长 美第奇家族卖给你这件大衣多少钱?
Tell me, Captain, how much did you give the Medicis for your coat?
我在罗马买的 不是佛罗伦萨
I bought it in Rome, not Florence.
欧洲所有的布料都要用这里的明矾矿
Every dyed fabric in Europe uses alum from these mines
来稳固着色
to fix the dye.
你知道吗 教皇庇护二世
Did you know, Pope Pius II
把这里的矿产赐给美第奇家族
gave this mining concern to the Medicis
以偿还教皇的债务
in return for forgiveness of papal debt.
从那以后 每交易一件连衣裙 床单和衬衫
And since then, every frock, sheet and shirt
佛罗伦萨都会赚到一部分提成
has had a portion of its price going to Florence.
今天我们一举三得
Today we killed three birds with one stone.
我们夺回了罗马的矿产
We took back what was rightfully Rome's.
我们铲除了美第奇的一笔收入来源
We eliminated a lucrative source of Medici income
最重要的是...
and most importantly...
我们送出了战函
we sent a message.
这简直是在复制艺术品
This is an art, this pursuit.
我只喜欢创作
I like just making one of something.
你最好习惯点 我们还有好多要生产呢
Well, you'd better get used to it. We've got plenty more copies to go.
我要习惯什么?
What is it that I'm getting used to?
习惯杀人变得麻木吗?
Making each soldier's death indistinguishable from the last?
莱昂纳多 请到宫殿来一下
Leonardo, you're needed at the palace.
你当起跑差了 老爸?
You playing errand boy now, Father?
在国难关头 我们要听从征召
In these traitorous times, we fill any role required.
快点 美第奇家族可没耐心等你
Come on. The Medicis are none of them patient men.
你们不能来
Not you two.
这是国家大事 非同小可
This is state business, not a sideshow.
你们能坐在这里
If you are in this room,
是因为你们是我最信任的人
it is because you reside in my innermost circle of trust.
我信任你们
And if you are in my circle,
是因为我们对佛罗伦萨有共同的期望
it is because we share a common vision for Florence.
我们希望佛罗伦萨可以被世代铭记
A city that will be remembered for centuries
永为创新和艺术的焦点
as a cynosure of innovation and artistry.
我收到了托尔法镇夸特隆司令官的消息
I have received word from Tolfa, Commander Quattrone,
瑞阿里奥伯爵进攻了我们的明矾矿
that Count Riario has attacked our alum mine.
这是对我们的宣战
This is a casus belli. An act of war.
和平时期的佛罗伦萨很繁荣
It is easy to be for Florence in times of peace.
但战争时期不会
Not so in times of war.
有谁不能支持我们的 请离开
Those who cannot stand with us should leave.
现在当懦夫 总比将来叛国好
It is better to be a coward now than a traitor later.
我近日失去了最信任的顾问
I recently lost my most trusted advisor to treachery.
他现在正在狱里等待他的刑罚
He currently sits in the Bargello awaiting his fate on the wheel.
美第奇家族惩罚叛贼
In the Medici court, we punish treason
奖赏功臣
and we reward service.
带来这封信的年轻人 请上前来
Would the young man who brought me this scroll please come forward.
请告诉我们 你是从哪拿到这信的?
So tell us, please, how did you come by the scroll?
一个明矾矿工给我的 先生
A Tolfan miner, sir.
瑞阿里奥伯爵杀了所有人
Count Riario killed all but one
只留下他一个人送来这封信
whom he tasked with delivering the scroll.
你能告诉我们信的内容吗?
And would you tell us what it says?
瑞阿里奥有一支军队 先生
Riario has an army, sir.
他要你对罗马俯首称臣 否则将占领佛罗伦萨
He intends to occupy Florence unless you do as Rome asks.
这是那矿工告诉你的?
Did the miner convey this to you?
他是个平民 先生 我想他不认识字
He's a simple man, sir. I doubt he can read.
所以你私拆了信封
So you broke the seal
然后给其他人看了内容?
and revealed its contents to others?
逮捕他
Arrest him.
- 先拿他试试刑轮!  - 求求你 先生! 不要!
- Warm up the wheel with his bones!  - Please, sir! No!
对背叛美第奇家族的人我绝不留情
I will show no mercy to those who betray the Medici name.
在城里你们每个人都各负其责
Each of you has a responsibility to this community.
保护 发明和维护秩序
To protect. To invent. To maintain order.
支持
To support.
维护美第奇的神圣荣誉
To uphold the sacred honor of the Medici legacy.
我们都知道 这一天迟早会到来
We all knew this day would come.
我们不会屈服
We will not submit.
我们要战斗
We will fight.
为佛罗伦萨而战!
Alla Battaglia Firenze!
我也有嫌疑
I think I have a cat in my bag.
你也要处决我 是吗?
Would you like to kick that, too?
够了
Enough.
一座被作为革新和艺术焦点的城市
A city that will be remembered for centuries to come,
将被铭记数百年
as a cynosure for innovation and artistry.
这是直接引用了在十九岁继承基业之前
That's a direct quote from Becchi's counsel to you,
贝奇给你这个吓得要死的空想家的建议
when you were a shit-scared 19-year-old poet about to ascend the throne.
- 现在别提  - 就要现在提
- Not now.  - Yes, now.
强硬和残忍是不一样的 洛伦佐
There's a difference between strength and cruelty, Lorenzo.
不要再用暴政了
Leave cruelty to Sixtus and his brutes,
不然就不是罗马...
or it won't be Rome...
而是我们自己的人民起来对抗我们
it'll be our own people who move against us.
帮我个忙 兄弟
Do me a kindness, brother.
等我去见瑞阿里奥伯爵的时候
When I ride out to meet Count Riario,
守在家里
stay home.
女士们先生们 我有圣阿里比诺斯破碎的脚骨
Ladies and gentlemen, I have here the shattered ankle bone of St Alibinus.
一块小小的碎骨可以保佑远离
A single shard of which is guaranteed to protect,
所有的海盗和暴徒
against all pirates and all ruffians.
如果再多出几个铜钱
And, for a few soldi more,
还可以买到受人尊敬的圣白苏烈士的手指!
the fingers of the esteemed martyr St Bessus!
- 是"拜苏" 你个白痴!  - 哦 得了吧
- It's Bess-us, you idiot!  - Oh, piss off.
- 怎么这么多人?  - 还有谁要?
- What causes this commotion?  - Who else wants some?
人们是来看死刑的
People have gathered for an execution.
金泰尔・贝奇应该等到满月才行刑的吧
Gentile Becchi wasn't meant to be brought up until the full moon.
不 不是贝奇 是个随从
No, not Becchi. A servant.
拜他所赐 瑞阿里奥的口信已经像野火一样散播开来
Thanks to him, word of Riario's incursion has spread like wildfire,
所以洛伦佐要杀一儆百
and Lorenzo wants to make an example.
看行刑的人们真是无情
The Confraternity of Death are such vultures.
要有人为罪犯祈祷
Someone has to pray for the condemned.
这不适合女士观看
This is ugly business for a lady.
不
No.
就算是女士也要支持美第奇家族对抗间谍
Even a lady must support the Medicis against spies.
天啊
God.
这要执行多久?
How long will this take?
可能数小时
It can last hours.
背叛洛伦佐的人都会受到神的庇护
God help any man who betrays Lorenzo.
你在看什么?
What are you reading?
祈祷书
A Book of Hours.
肯定是拉丁文原版的
In the original Latin, no doubt.
我一直很讨厌那种语言
I always hated that language.
从你的学习态度就能看出来
As was evident in your studies.
也许你是个糟糕的老师
Perhaps you were simply a piss-poor teacher.
也许吧
Perhaps.
弄成这样 真的很抱歉
I'm sorry it's come to this.
嗯
Mm.
你为什么不跟我们说你家需要钱
Why didn't you tell us about your family's need for money.
我不会以自己亲属的不幸来为你们添麻烦
I would never have troubled you with my relatives' mishaps.
却接受罗马的钱?
But you would take coin from Rome?
扪心自问 孩子
Ask yourself, my boy.
如果我被金钱所鼓动 为什么还不花掉?
If money had motivated me, why wouldn't it have been spent already?
就随便放在我的住所里 等着被发现
Instead of lying conveniently in my quarters awaiting discovery.
还带着罗马教皇的封印
Along with the papal seals of Rome.
我也想相信你
I want to believe.
你辅佐了我的祖父科西莫 我的父亲
You counseled my grandfather Cosimo. My father.
你毕生都献给了佛罗伦萨
You've given your life in service to Florence.
一直在尽心竭力守护美第奇家族之名
Always doing your best to protect the Medici name.
等我死后 朱利亚诺
But when I am gone, Giuliano,
我将无法再提供这种保护
I will no longer be able to provide such protection.
你是不是无辜的呢?
Are you innocent of these charges or not?
- 当然是  - 那你为什么不争辩?
- Of course I am.  - Then why don't you fight them?
因为你哥哥已经听不进劝告了
Because your brother is incapable of listening.
洛伦佐已经被怒气蒙蔽了
Lorenzo is consumed with wrath.
让他无法察觉身边的危险
It blinds him to the dangers circling him.
我们的人中有叛徒
There is a traitor in our midst.
等我死后 洛伦佐会放松警惕
After I am dead and Lorenzo lowers his guard,
而叛徒还在
the traitor will still be here.
人们会低估你 朱利亚诺
People underestimate you, Giuliano.
而这种观念使你特别适合
Yet that perceived weakness makes you uniquely suited,
从暗处抓出间谍
to flushing out a spy from cover.
照顾好你哥哥
Look after your brother.
他比以往更需要你
He needs you. Now more than ever.
瑞阿里奥会穿过瓦达诺谷
Riario will advance from the south,
从南面进攻
through the Valdarno Valley.
我们会在侧面布置武器
We'll place weapons on all sides,
不过大部队会在这里交手
but the majority will meet his men here.
我们会占人数优势 武器超越他们
We'll be outnumbered. They'll be outgunned.
就靠十门炮? 你确定吗?
With ten guns? Are you certain?
我们在铸造更多大炮
We're casting more muskets.
我保证 你根本用不着开炮
I promise you you'll never have to fire them.
有时候...
Sometimes...
当你的敌人只顾着杀戮的时候
when all your enemy knows is killing,
一个小骗局就能奏效
a simple deception can suffice.
瑞阿里奥比你想象的要聪明得多 达芬奇
Riario is far more clever than you think, DaVinci.
你的智慧无法帮我们解开这个局
Your wit won't get us out of this one.
不过你的武器可以
Only your weapons will.
而且我保证会开炮的
And I promise you they will fire.
- 大人!  - 指挥官
- Magnifico!  - Commander.
- 艺术家  - 其实是战争工程师
- Artista.  - War engineer, actually.
你骑的马很好啊
That's a very handsome stallion you have there.
- 安达卢西亚种吗?  - 是
- Andalusian, no?  - Mm.
卡斯提尔的伊莎贝拉女王私人赏赐给我的
Given to me personally by Queen Isabella of Castile.
我听说过这些安达卢西亚马
I've heard of these Andalusians.
我知道这马更容易得缺血性疾病
I understand the breed's prone to ischemic diseases,
降低血流速度 尤其是肠系统
reduced blood flow, especially to the intestines,
会导致肛塞
which can lead to some unfortunate anal blockage.
显然你已经习惯如影随形的马粪味了
Undoubtedly, you're used to the smell of shit following you wherever you go.
哼
Hmm.
为了避免更大的杀戮
In an effort to avoid further bloodshed,
大人提出了一些要求
his Eminence has extended a list of demands.
首先 佛罗伦萨必须正式接受
First, Florence will formally embrace into its bosom,
弗朗西斯科・萨尔维亚蒂出任比萨大主教
Francesco Salviati as Archbishop of Pisa.
其次 美第奇银行必须清空所有圣座的债务
Second, the Medici Bank will forgive the Holy See of all debts.
再次 还要解除
And third, you will release,
某些工匠的债务合约
certain artisans from their contractual obligations,
让他们可以把自己的才华
so that they might employ their gifts,
使用在圣座的新教堂上
in service of His Holiness's new chapel.
圣座需要哪些艺术家?
And in which artist is His Holiness interested?
一个叫... 彼得・佩鲁吉诺
One... Pietro Perugino.
一个叫桑德罗・波提切利
One Sandro Botticelli.
- 天啊...  - 还有
- Oh, Jesus...  - Ooh.
莱昂纳多・达芬奇
Leonardo DaVinci.
我宁愿让鳗鱼咬掉我的蛋蛋
I'd rather have my testicles gnawed off by conger eels.
- 这要求可以满足  - 我们要是不答应呢?
- Well, that can be arranged.  - And if we don't capitulate?
我的部队将会占领佛罗伦萨
My forces will occupy Florence.
我的大炮会把你的人炸成碎片
My guns will cut your men to ribbons.
你那些传说中的转轮炮?
Your fabled pipe organ muskets?
是的 可以炸死一些 不过不是全部
Well, yes, they will cut down some of them, but not all.
感谢朱利亚诺
Thanks to Giuliano's bumbling,
我得以知道你们铸造了十门炮
I was aware that you possessed ten guns,
通过我对它们的观察
and given that I've observed them,
我简单地推算了它们的循环射速
I simply deduced their cyclic rate of fire.
每一次装填后可以进行
Between them, they're capable of launching,
33次齐射 共333颗炮弹
33 volleys comprising 333 discharges.
现在... 我们假设...
Now, let's... Let's assume that...
其中有三分之二击中了目标
two-thirds of them hit their mark.
不过你们的人在重新装填的时候会怎么样呢?
But what happens while your brave militiamen are reloading?
我剩下的四百铁骑会进攻
My remaining 400 ride out.
对 是的 以你们珍贵的人民作为目标
And, yes, we will use your precious Florentines as target practice.
你面对的是一座坚城 瑞阿里奥
You face a walled city, Riario.
我们至少可以抵御你们半年
We can hold you off for six months at the least.
只需要一个内应就能打开坚城
It takes but one person to open the gates from the inside.
你真的相信在这半年间
Do you truly believe that in those months,
圣座的召唤
the call of the Holy Father,
无法感召佛罗伦萨的任何一个灵魂吗?
won't be honored by a single soul in Florence?
你有24小时考虑圣座的条件
You have 24 hours to ponder the Holy Father's offer.
祝你们愉快
Enjoy your day.
我们需要更多的炮 达芬奇
We need more guns, DaVinci.
我们的性命决定于此
Our lives depend on it.
我们不是应该铸造大炮
Shouldn't we be building guns,
或者至少准备防御进攻吗?
or at least preparing for the invasion?
- 我在画草图  - 不过是石榴的
- I'm sketching.  - Pomegranates.
没什么能逃过你的眼睛
Nothing escapes you.
瑞阿里奥伯爵就快进攻了
Count Riario is nearly upon us.
我当然知道瑞阿里奥要来了!
I know damn well where Riario is!
- 我们在这做什么?  - 我自己也纳闷
- What are we doing here?  - I wonder about that myself.
请原谅 夫人
Excuse us, Signora.
你对自己的草图也不认真 艺术家
You're rather careless with your sketches, Artista.
有一些忘在我丈夫的书房里了
You left a sheaf of them in my husband's study.
你不是应该为佛罗伦萨的安全服务的吗?
Shouldn't you be laboring for the security of Florence?
石榴上还有些问题 目前还没有解决
There's something about this pomegranate. I can't define it yet.
不过希腊人告诉我们任何事情都可以变化
But the Greeks teach us everything can be everything.
任何事物之间都可以互相转化
And everything can be turned into everything else.
如果我们看不到其中的结构
If we can't see the pattern in God's architecture,
那只是因为我们观察得还不够近
it's because we're not looking closely enough.
你还要你的草图吗?
Would you like your sketches back?
洛伦佐所有的藏品里
Of all of Lorenzo's treasures,
只有这个小东西吸引了你的眼球
it was this bit of carved stone that caught your eye.
你丈夫给你说过吗? 它是从何而来?
Has your husband ever mentioned it to you? Where it came from.
我估计是继承的遗产
I believe he inherited it.
可能就是从隔壁房间的那个人
Perhaps from a man in the next room.
一个魔术师
A magician.
这是洛伦佐的祖父科西莫
Lorenzo's grandfather. Cosimo.
他连办公室都不需要就能治理这座城市
He ruled this city without ever holding office.
哦 他确实有一套
Oh, there's something about him.
随时欢迎你来研究他
You're welcome to study him at any time.
不过现在我希望你能接着铸造大炮 好吗?
But for now I'd rather you returned to your guns. No?
我来佛罗伦萨不是为了屈从于罗马统治的
I didn't come to Florence to live under Roman rule.
达芬奇
DaVinci.
作为回报 请笑纳
A treat. For indulging me.
感谢你能与我见面
Thank you for meeting with me,
特别是罗马正在咄咄相逼
especially with all the concerns about Rome.
我知道这不好 可事情发展至此 我别无他法
I know this is unorthodox, but circumstances forced my hand.
你也知道贝奇的事了
You know what's happened to Becchi.
指控已经成立
The accusations that have been made.
我不相信他是叛徒
I don't believe he's a traitor.
你想让我怎么做?
What do you want me to do?
克拉丽斯已经准备好支持贝奇了
Clarice has already agreed to advocate for Becchi.
你掌控着我哥哥另一半的心 你也能这么做吗?
You own the other half of my brother's heart. Will you do the same?
你确定他是无辜的?
Are you so sure he's innocent?
我相信可以证明这一点
I believe we can prove it.
贝奇已经给了我建议
Becchi has been giving me counsel.
跟他合作 我觉得我们可以抓出真正的叛徒
Working with him, I know we can trap the real traitor.
求你 夫人
Please, Signora.
炉温正常
Temperature's right.
莱昂
Leo.
肾脏肿大的那个工头需要你帮助
The fat-kidneyed foreman requires your help.
我们对洛伦佐的祖先了解多少?
What do we know of Lorenzo's ancestors?
他父亲是个好人 不过不健康 伙计
His father was a good, but sickly, man.
生活在他父亲的阴影之下... 科西莫
Who lived in the shadow of his father... Cosimo.
喔 是吗? 这他妈的有什么关系?
Wow. Really? How in fuck does this matter?
罗马的佣兵已经兵临城下了
Rome's mercenaries are upon us.
克拉丽斯・奥尔西尼今天给我的
Clarice Orsini gave me this today.
她说是洛伦佐继承来的
She said Lorenzo inherited it.
你是累坏了 看看你
You're exhausted. Look at you.
在我们需要更多大炮的时候还在研究这个小玩意 简直疯了
Fixating on bric-a-brac when we need more guns. It's insane.
它手里的钥匙和犹太人那把是一样的
The keys on it are identical to the ones from the Jew.
天穹 叶之书
The Vault of Heaven. The Book of Leaves.
美第奇怎么会知道这些?
How do the Medicis figure into it all?
莱昂 我就是不明白一个壁炉台上的古董
Leo, I just don't see how a fucking mantelpiece antique,
怎么能从瑞阿里奥剑下拯救我们的脖子
keeps Riario's swords from our fucking necks.
天啊 琐罗 你就不能安生一会?
Christ, Zo. Can you just drop it for one minute?
一定要这么频繁得证明自己的无知吗?
Do you have to prove your ignorance so damn often?
当拜占庭帝国围攻君士坦丁堡第一次使用大炮
When the Byzantine Empire used the first cannons,
对付土耳其人的时候
against the Ottomans during the siege of Constantinople,
土耳其人溃退了
the Turks were forced to flee.
30年后 他们带着自己的大炮回来了
30 years later, they returned with cannons of their own.
更大的大炮
Bigger cannons.
经过55天的围攻之后...
And after a 55-day siege left such destruction...
城市已经面目全非
that the city will never be the same.
君士坦丁堡沦陷
Constantinople fell.
那么我们就要一直保证自己拥有更大的大炮
Then we've always got to make sure we've got the biggest cannon.
哦...
Oh...
永无止境
It never ends.
除非...
Unless...
除非我在这里终结它
Unless I end it here.
住手! 会爆炸的!
Don't! That will cause an explosion!
住手! 啊!
Don't! Aargh!
大师 你都做了些什么?
Maestro, what have you done?
把我们的命运锁死了
Sealed our fucking fate.
请宽恕我 神父 原谅我的罪恶
Bless me, Father, for I have sinned.
你上一次忏悔是多久前了?
How long has it been since your last confession?
我... 羞于启齿
I'm... embarrassed to say.
快一年了
Nearly a year.
哦
Oh.
我今晚已经跟很多忏悔者谈过了 孩子
I have spoken with many shamed penitents tonight, child.
刑轮让人们想到了惩罚
The wheel reminds people of the punishments,
还在等待着那些没有向圣父忏悔的灵魂
awaiting those not reconciled with Our Father.
太可怕了
It's horrid.
我恐怕亲手把别人送进了同样的酷刑
I fear I myself drive someone toward a similar agony.
夏娃的每位女儿都面对这同样的窘境
Every daughter of Eve faces the same dilemma.
我不诚实
I have been untrue.
现在却是别人在为此受苦
And now someone else is suffering for it.
而且他要承受无法想象的痛苦...
And he will endure unimaginable pain...
- 都是因我的错  - 请原谅
- and it's my fault.  - If I may.
我听说过一些关于你婚姻的传言
I have heard something of the state of your marriage.
如果你能给予 哪怕是最小的
If you can offer up, even the smallest,
最轻微的宽容
the tenderest bit of mercy,
我肯定会你会得到回报的
I have no doubt it will be taken very well.
- 宽容是要冒险的  - 却能得到报答
- Mercy has its risks.  - And rewards.
骗子!
Liar!
"佛罗伦萨的良民们 美第奇家族在带领你们走向死亡"
"Good people of Florence, the Medicis are leading you to death."
你们一定要赞扬一下瑞阿里奥
You have to give Riario some credit.
他知道如何恐吓他的猎物
He knows how to intimidate his prey.
据说瑞阿里奥带了两千人来屠城
People say Riario has 2,000 men to burn the city.
我听说有三千人
I heard 3,000.
城市会没事的 我来保证这一点
The city will be safe. I'll make sure of it.
骄傲是一种以命相抵的罪恶 艺术家
Pride is a deadly sin, Artista.
队长!
Il Capitano!
我没想到你还是个虔诚的教徒
I didn't take you for a religious zealot.
一个恃强凌弱的混蛋 没错 还虔诚?
A bully and an asshole, yes. A zealot?
只是...
It's...
我对自己的家庭虔诚
I'm zealous about my family.
我们每晚都在祈祷你不要把这座城市带往灭亡
We pray every night that you're not leading this city to destruction.
什么? 我有那么大的力量 真的?
What? I have that much power, do I?
自从你牵扯上美第奇家族 我们增加的只有麻烦
We've had nothing but trouble since you talked your way into the Medici court.
也许是因为就此事来说上帝站在家族这边
Perhaps God is on the Count's side in this business.
任何与那个空想家为伍的神明
I don't believe in any god,
都不值得我信仰
who would side with that pig's bladder.
你在亵渎神灵
You blaspheme.
像你这样的神经艺术家正在把佛罗伦萨变成蛾摩拉(圣经中的罪恶之都)
Men like you artistic perverts are turning Florence into Gomorrah.
你正走在通往不灭业火的捷径
You're beating a quick path to the everlasting bonfire,
还拖着我们跟你一起
and dragging us all with you.
我可以更快得直接把你送进业火
I'll send you to the bonfire even sooner.
我知道你剑术比我高超 达芬奇
I know you're a better swordsman than I, DaVinci.
不过...
Still...
我戳中了你的软肋 是吧?
I've struck the bone, eh?
在你需要利刃对付瑞阿里奥的时候
Do you really want to blunt the edge of your blade on me
真的想在我身上砍钝自己的刀锋吗?
when you may need it sharp for Riario?
你喝多了 莱昂纳多
You're drunk, Leonardo.
来啊!
Come on!
天啊
Oh, my God.
上帝
Jesus.
我听说了铸造作坊的事情
I heard what happened at the metal works.
你不是这样的 达芬奇
You're better than this, Leonardo.
我觉得自己可以拯救佛罗伦萨 我觉得...
I thought I could save Florence. I thought...
我的才华已经足够 可惜不是的
my talents would be enough, but they aren't.
我一无所有
I've got nothing.
也因为我
And because of me,
明早洛伦佐只能被迫投降
tomorrow morning, Lorenzo will be forced to surrender.
别这么说 佛罗伦萨和罗马在你出生之前已经如此
No, please. Florence and Rome have been at it since before you were born.
- 这是政治  - 不 这是...
- It's politics.  - No, it's...
是私事
It's personal.
我拥有他们想要的东西
I have something they want.
对 你的才华
Yes. Your talent.
教皇想要我的才华
The Pope wants my talent.
瑞阿里奥想要我的钥匙
Riario wants my key.
- 什么钥匙?  - 那把钥匙...
- What key?  - The key from...
没什么
Nothing.
过来
Come here.
如果你感到负担...
If something burdens you...
也许放开它会更好些
maybe it's better just to let it go.
等等 慢点
Wait. Wait.
怎么了?
What?
洛伦佐就是这样要求我的
That's what Lorenzo requires of me.
你为什么要炸毁自己的大炮?
Why did you destroy your guns?
洛伦佐
Lorenzo.
他看着我的眼睛告诉我 我是个发明家
He looked me in the eye and told me I was an inventor.
可这不是发明 这是...
But this isn't invention. This is...
这是复制 我铸造五门 他们铸造五十门
It's escalation. I build five, they build 50.
你估计是我见过最可爱的人
You might be the loveliest man I've ever known.
嘿
Hey.
你为什么说的时候如此悲伤?
Why do you say it with such sadness?
也许是因为我觉得我们谁也配不上你
Maybe it's because I think none of us are worthy of you.
为什么研究石榴?
Why the pomegranates?
还不知道
I don't know yet.
你知道...
Do you know...
其实... 在珀尔塞福涅离开冥界时
Now... Hades tricked Persephone into eating pomegranates,
珀尔塞福涅: 宙斯之女 被冥王劫持娶作冥后
是冥王骗她吃下了石榴
when she left the underworld.
她说是魔法迫使她回到他的身边
She said that their magic forced her to return to him.
是真的
It's true.
你走的时候应该带个走
You should take one with you when you go.
不是魔法让你我相遇相交的 莱昂纳多
It's not magic that binds me to you, Leonardo.
我希望你能杀了瑞阿里奥那个杂种
I hope you kill that bastard Riario.
莱昂纳多!
Leonardo!
你还有胆留在佛罗伦萨?
Oh, so you have the gall to remain in Florence?
你到底是勇敢还是傻到不透气
You're either brave or unimaginably stupid.
都算是吧
A bit of both.
你毁掉了我们的努力 为什么?
You sabotage our efforts. Why?
大炮无法终结这一切
The guns wouldn't have ended this.
就凭你这点战争的经验 你就认定这样了 是吗?
With all your experience in waging war, you decided that, did you?
你个...
You little...
该死!
Fuck!
真难以置信 我竟然信了你
I can't believe I trusted you.
你这个混蛋 骗子 地摊贩子!
You, a bastard. A charlatan. A peddler of knick-knacks!
我弟弟说得对 我相信你实在太傻了 太傻了!
My brother was right. I was a fool to believe in you. A fool!
我唯一能做的是自己去做瑞阿里奥的人质
My only recourse is to offer myself as Riario's hostage,
还得祈祷能得到他的宽恕
and I'll have to pray that if I put myself at his mercy,
让他不再劫掠佛罗伦萨
that he will forego pillaging Florence.
我还得祈祷他能保证克拉丽斯和我们孩子的安全
I'll have to pray that he'll grant Clarice and our children safe passage.
And I'll have to pray that every trace of my name and my legacy，
祈祷我的名字和家族
不会从街上被清理掉!
isn't struck from the streets!
你收拾好自己的收藏跟我去见面的地方吧
You gather what little you hold dear and you meet me in the field.
在我被迫接受罗马的条件的时候 希望你能见证
I want you by my side when I am forced to accept Rome's terms.
而且如果瑞阿里奥想要你...
And if Riario wants you...
就他妈的把你给他
he can fucking have you.
尼科 很高兴再见到你
Nico, it is good to see you again.
估计你的手快好了吧
I trust your hand is mending.
我们直接谈谈投降的条件吧
Let us go straight to the terms of surrender.
好
Indeed.
我确定...
I have certain...
需要一些保证
require certain assurances.
因为佛罗伦萨和这里的人民是我最关切的...
Florence and its citizens are my chief concern...
抱歉 等等
Sorry. Sorry.
呃 我们明确了是哪一方要投降对吧?
Um, we are clear whose surrender we're discussing here?
是你们
It's yours.
达芬奇...
DaVinci...
尼科 给伯爵和司令看看我们的礼品吧?
Nico, would you show the Count and Captain General our gift?
看吧 既然你已经推算了我大炮的射速
Now, since you'd calculated the capacity of my guns,
我也试着改进了佛罗伦萨的装备
I've endeavored to improve Florence's odds.
只是简单的数字问题
It's a question of mathematics.
怎样用最节省的方式填装所有的弹丸
How to pack a group of spheres in the most economic fashion.
既然大自然总是使用最有效的方式达到目的
And since nature always employs the most efficient means to achieve her ends,
我就从中获得了灵感
I've taken inspiration from her.
我管这个叫集束炸弹
I call it the cluster bombard.
炮弹中是一包更小的炸弹
The casing houses a grouping of smaller explosives,
阿基米德体形态
an Archimedean solid,
由钢制层分离
which is separated by iron spacers.
所以当炮弹着地的时候 弹片形成一个喷泉
So when the bombard lands, it fragments into a fountain of shrapnel.
我估计每颗炸弹可以干掉你一打的人还有他们的坐骑
I estimate one bombard could take out a dozen of your men and their mounts.
我知道你在想什么
Now, I know what you're thinking.
你在想 "哦 还可以
You're thinking, "Well, fair enough.
炸弹只有能够装填发射才能发挥作用"
A bombard's really only as good as one's ability to lob it."
对 很对 你想得不错
So, fair enough. You'd be right.
不过...
However...
琐罗!
Zo!
动手
Let's go.
很有说服力
Impressive.
我怎么能相信你的发明是能用的?
But how do I know that contraption even works?
请允许我用一个小型的模型演示
Allow me to demonstrate on a smaller scale.
首先 我们把炮弹点燃
First, we light the bombard.
然后发射... 就这样
Then we fire it... like so.
当然真正满载的炸弹 装的不是烟火
The real, full-scale bombard doesn't carry fireworks, of course.
我们将用火焰和杀伤力笼罩你的军队
We will rain flame and destruction down on your men,
让他们想起圣经传说中的毁灭
recalling Biblical devastation of old.
你的人散落在这片土地上的骸骨碎片
The peasants will pick the bone fragments of your men
农民们估计要花几十年才能捡完
from these fields for decades to come.
你... 赢得的一切 将会从记忆中被清除
You... everything you've accomplished, will fade from memory.
反而我们的胜利将会被传承数百年
Whereas our victory will be lionized for centuries.
也许
Perhaps.
也许今天发生的事情不算什么
Or perhaps regardless of what happens today,
传说的会是另一个故事 或者没有故事
the opposite tale will be told, or no tale at all.
是这样 曾经有一个人告诉我...
You see, a man once told me...
历史只是谎言
History is a lie.
干得好 艺术家
Well played, Artista.
你... 虽然你记性不错
You'd... You'd do well to remember, though,
战争有很多的方面
that a war is waged on many fronts.
驾! 驾!
Hyah! Hyah!
解除了好大的威胁 莱昂纳多
You pulled off quite a feat, Leonardo.
我真想看它开炮 想象这个残杀
I would have liked to see it fire. Imagine the carnage.
罗马估计要连续办几个月的葬礼
Rome would have been holding funerals for months.
这个弩其实根本不能用
The crossbow it doesn't actually work.
这其实不是武器 而是一件艺术品
It's more a feat of art than weaponry.
这个赝品...
This sham...
是宿醉艺术家的作品
is the work of drunken artists.
表演的意义远大于真正的武器价值
They're more skilled in stage props than armaments.
一夜之间我们怎么可能造出来真正的装备?
How on earth can we have built the real device in one night?
就算造出来了 弹射这玩意的皮筋力量也荒唐的可笑
Even if I had, the drawstring needed to fire the damn thing would have been ludicrous.
- 你看吧  - 你把我们的命运当做儿戏的赌注?
- Look at it.  - You wagered our fate on a bluff?
- 是  - 那你只是为我们赢得了暂时的喘息
- I did.  - You only bought us a temporary reprieve.
你不可能唬住罗马一辈子
You can't keep on bluffing Rome forever.
不能吗?
Can't we?
生命宝贵 洛伦佐
Life's precious, Lorenzo.
叛徒亦如是
Even a traitor's.
我相信...
I believe...
是你祖父科西莫...
it was your grandfather, Cosimo...
发表过相关的意见
who voiced a pertinent sentiment.
"我们知道应该原谅我们的敌人
"We read that we ought to forgive our enemies.
却不知道要原谅我们的朋友"
We do not read that we ought to forgive our friends."
抱歉 兄弟 我只是稍稍休息一下
Sorry, brother. I was just having a rest.
你是来帮囚犯做忏悔的?
Have you come to minister to the condemned?
好
Right.
我感谢你的来访 不过我已经接受了这一切
I appreciate the visit but I've already made peace with my maker.
夫人
Signora.
你
You.
是你把那些文件放进了我的房间
You're the one that slipped those documents into my quarters.
你变节多久了?
How long have they owned you?
几年了
A few years.
那他们收买你...
Then they approached you...
是在我与洛伦佐在一起之前
Before Lorenzo and I were involved.
不管他们承诺了什么 都不会兑现的
Whatever promise they made, they will not honor it.
你对我的处境
You have no idea,
一无所知
of my circumstances.
这不仅关乎佛罗伦萨 罗马
There's more to this than Florence or Rome,
还有我的性命
or my life.
你来干什么 夫人?
Why are you here, Signora?
因为我不想看到你被钉在刑轮上活活打死
Because I do not wish to see you broken on a wheel.
什么?
What?
毒芹
Hemlock.
怎么会?
How?
从罗马教廷密室偷来的一件武器
A weapon stolen from the Secret Archives in the Vatican.
这一件带着一针毒剂
A misericorde, modified with a single dose of poison.
几乎感觉不到疼痛
Its bite is almost never noticed.
不会有证据指向
So no evidence will arise,
洛伦佐的爱人
implicating Lorenzo's lover.
请当做是我的慈悲
Consider it mercy.
这是我能提供的最迅速 最没有痛苦的死法
This is the fastest and most painless death I can offer.
我需要亲眼见证
And I will see that it takes.
这不是慈悲
This isn't mercy.
只是你... 在灭口
This is you... tying off loose ends.
罗马的选择是高明的
Rome chose well.
- 卫兵!  - 抱歉
- Guard!  - I'm sorry.
我也希望还有其他的办法
I wish there was another way.
贝奇!
Becchi!
卫兵!
Guards!
卫兵 快!
Guards, quickly!
是毒芹
Hemlock.
- 贝奇不会自杀的  - 证据确凿
- Becchi would not have done this.  - The vial speaks for itself.
而且你也已经习惯不相信
And you have a history of not believing things,
贝奇所做的事情
that Becchi has clearly done.
问题在于 弟弟
Question is, brother,
是谁给贝奇送来了毒药?
who brought Becchi this poison?
会不会是支持他的人?
Was it someone who sympathizes with his plight?
如果是我的话 哥哥 我不会带着面具的
If I were to defy you, brother, I wouldn't don a mask to do it.
你还在乎什么?
But what do you care?
叛徒死了 佛罗伦萨安全了
The traitor is dead, Florence is secure,
你还要给个战争工程师奖赏
and you've a war engineer to fete.
最好是在今晚的会上
All is well in the Republic tonight.
这份命令上写的名字和指控
The names and charges written on this paper,
要求我们立刻提起最高注意
require our immediate attention as Priori.
匿名告发信?
An anonymous denunciation?
告发人不重要
The author's unimportant.
此事需要调查
This matter demands investigation.
我要提醒你考虑牵涉其中的人
I'd caution you to consider who will be implicated.
作为执法者 你们有责任维护律法
As Priori, you are duty bound to uphold the law,
不管涉及到谁
unconcerned by who whomever it may incriminate.
提审这里提到的人 队长
Interrogate the victim mentioned here, Captain.
他只要认罪 就逮捕他
Once he confirms the charges, make your arrest.
瞧瞧你!
Wow, look at you!
威尼斯马裤 带天鹅绒 带锦缎
Venetian breeches, bit of velvet, bit of brocade.
你用美第奇的奖赏买的?
Did you buy those with your Medici vouchers?
你担心什么?
What concern is it of yours?
是谁打白条召集众人
Who traded in chits to muster the men,
把你的大假弩拉出城的? 忘了?
to sneak your phony crossbow out of the city? Hm?
是谁半夜冒着生命危险 把它组装起来的?
Who assembled all the pieces in the middle of the night, risking his life?
因为不是尼科 结果那个小屁孩子都受邀
Cos it wasn't Nico. Yet somehow that little bull's pizzle,
去洛伦佐的宫殿了我都没有
wins an invitation to Lorenzo's palazzo and I don't.
尼科没有因为下流行径 偷窃
Nico hasn't been arrested a dozen times for lewd behavior,
或者挖坟掘墓被逮捕过多次
and pickpocketing, grave robbing.
我今晚不能带你去 琐罗 抱歉
I can't have you there tonight, Zo. Sorry.
得体对这些人...
These people...
意味着一切
decorum means everything to them.
你的贵宾在哪里 洛伦佐?
Where is your guest of honor, Lorenzo?
如果是要表彰一位艺术家 那就应该是波提切利先生
If we're to praise an artist, perhaps it should be Signor Botticelli.
因为至少他到场了
At least he has blessed up with his presence.
一个已经誉满全城的人不需要其它荣誉了 哥哥
No need to honor someone who honors themselves so well, brother.
每次我发现自己在找达芬奇的时候 他都会...
Every time I find myself looking for DaVinci, he seems to have...
像烟雾一样消失
vanished like smoke.
你有什么原因要躲开聚会吗 大师?
Is there a reason you're avoiding the party, Maestro?
大家都等着你呢
It's being held in your honor.
有事情困扰着我 尼科
Something's needling me, Nico.
等我发现这...
Till I can discover what it...
哈!
Ha!
对了!
Yes!
老魔术师的微笑
The old magician's laughing.
我真是白痴
I'm an idiot.
提示再明显不过了
The symbols couldn't be clearer.
我是大地与星空之子
I am a son of Earth and Starry Heaven.
我渴了 求你了 从记忆之泉中
I am thirsty. Please give me something to drink,
取水给我喝
from the fountain of Memory.
密特拉之子的祷词 看
The invocation for the Sons of Mithras. Look.
牛在拉犁
A bull pulling a plow.
基督徒的插图 也是异教徒的大地标志
Christian iconography but it's also the pagan symbol for Earth.
布满星星的天空
A star-filled heaven.
圣杯 象征着喷泉
A chalice, symbolic of a fountain.
还有花朵 花名是法语的
And flowers. Ne M'oubliez Pas, in French.
勿忘草
Forget-me-nots.
记忆
Memory.
科西莫・美第奇...
Cosimo de Medici...
是密特拉之子
was a Son of Mithras.
看来我所有的疑问都汇聚到了一起
It's as if all my inquiries are converging.
就像一张撒开的网
It's as if a grand web is being spun.
无法想象的广阔和古老
One so incalculably wide and ancient,
以至于我才刚刚目及导它的范围
that I'm only now beginning to grasp its scope.
我已经向洛伦佐证明了自己
I have proven myself to Lorenzo.
赢得了他的信任
I've earned his trust.
是时候让他用爱心回报我了
It's time for him to repay me in kind.
怎样?
By doing what?
赞助一次探险
By funding an expedition.
去犹太人地图上指示的大陆
To the land indicated on the Jew's map.
一艘船 探险的补给
A ship, provisions for a journey.
天穹就在那 尼科
The Vault of Heaven is out there, Nico.
叶之书就在那里
It's harbing the Book of Leaves.
还有里面的知识 我能听到它在呼唤我
All the knowledge it contains, I can hear it calling to me.
魔术师在指引我的路
And the magician is leading me to it.
我的祖父科西莫有一个梦想
My grandfather, Cosimo, had a dream.
我们的街道和广场
That our streets and squares,
应该是科学 艺术和求知的天堂
would be a haven for science, art and learning.
最能代表这理想的佛罗伦萨子民
No son of Florence better represents those ideas,
就是莱昂纳多・达芬奇
than Leonardo DaVinci.
我赐你为...
I name you...
"施洗者约翰"之大师
Grand Master of the Order of St John the Baptist,
佛罗伦萨的守护者
patron saint of Florence.
请允许我向你们介绍古典智慧的真实化身
I give you the living embodiment of classical brilliance.
莱昂纳多・达芬奇
Leonardo DaVinci.
来吧 大师 给我们说几句吧?
Please, Maestro, won't you grant us a few words?
佛罗伦萨最大的产品就是灵感
Florence's greatest export has always been its ideas.
我们的共和制代表着追求的前沿
Our Republic represents the cutting edge of inquiry.
我们在发明未来
We are inventing the future.
但是只有不停追求才能保证我们一直生气勃勃
But we can only remain vital if we keep on pushing outwards,
所以我请求一个新的开始
so I propose a bold new step.
我发现了一片大陆 殿下 在西面
I have learned of a land, your Magnificence, to the west.
未曾表明过却一定蕴含着奇异
It's largely uncharted but it's certain to contain wonders.
现在 得到您的资助 我想开始一次探险
Now, with your patronage, I shall mount an expedition.
我们要驶向...
We will voyage...
德拉戈奈蒂队长 这么无礼是要干什么?
Captain Dragonetti, what is the meaning of this affront?
抱歉 阁下
My apologies, Signor.
有一项挖坟掘墓的罪名落到了您一位宾客的头上
A grave accusation has been levied against one of your guests.
我对此一无所知
I know nothing of any accusations.
请允许提醒你 纳扎雷诺 你是我的属下
May I remind you, Nazzareno, that you answer to me.
准确来说 我是法度的属下 殿下
Technically, I answer to the Signoria, your Magnificence.
您虽代表着法律 但也仅是一人之言
Of which you are but one voice.
我不能无视法度 阁下 这是规矩
I couldn't dissuade them, Signor. It's protocol.
我们只能服从
Our hands were tied.
那继续吧 队长
Go on then, Captain.
此事已经引起了值夜的官员注意
It has come to the attention of the Officers of the Night,
是通过匿名告发的方式
by means of secret denunciation,
有一位叫莱昂纳多・达芬奇的人
that one Leonardo di ser Piero DaVinci,
被认定违反了佛罗伦萨共和国的律法
has committed, in violation of the statutes of the Republic of Florence,
神赐的自然律法 还犯有鸡奸罪
and divine and natural law, the grievous act of sodomy.
此人需被立即羁押候审...
Said individual is to be immediately remanded...
那些是谎言 这是诽谤!
These are lies. This is slander!
所以他会被扣押
Whereupon he will remain,
直到治安官查清他有罪还是无罪
until the Magistrates ascertain his guilt or innocence.
若是有罪
Should he be found guilty,
他将会被游街示众到刑场
he will be led through the public squares to the Palace of Justice,
然后火刑至死...
and there be burned so that he dies...
直到肉体与灵魂分离
and his body is separated from his soul.
不! 你...
No! You...
这都是你做的 弗朗西斯科
This is your work, Francesco.
我能闻到阴谋的恶臭
I smell the Pazzi stench all over this charade.
指控是真的 洛伦佐
The denunciation is real, Lorenzo.
我们有污点证人
We've a victim willing to testify.
已经有五十年没有人因为这项罪名被判刑了
No-one has been sentenced for this crime for more than 50 years.
不过还是在律法之中
And yet it's still on the statute books.
如果你有意见 去找你先人科西莫说吧
If you've issues with it, take it up with your forebear Cosimo.
难道不是他修订了佛罗伦萨的宪法吗?
Was it not he who revised Florence's constitution?
还是你要以自己的看法凌驾于我们共和制的法律之上?
Or would you flout our fair Republic's laws as you see fit?
我认为我们还是生活在一个共和的体制之下
I was under the impression we lived in a democracy.
- 而不是独裁制  - 请伸手 先生
- Not a dictatorship.  - Your wrists, Signor.
早跟你说了走在通往业火的捷径上了 艺术家
Told you that you take the quick path to the bonfire, Artista.
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hd.cnscg.com/ ==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调：影子
时间轴：暗之忆
翻译：SceneryJuly 竺
校对：竺 影子